<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Archagon Was Here</title>
    <description>Alexei's pile o'stuff, featuring writing on software development, travel, photography, and more.
</description>
    <link>http://archagon.net/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://archagon.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 22:12:34 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 22:12:34 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>eGPU Redux: Sticking a GTX 1080 in an AKiTiO Thunder2</title>
        <description>
&lt;div class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://archagon.net/images/blog/egpu-2/header2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a year and a half since I wrote my article on &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/12/31/cheap-and-painless-egpu-thrills-on-a-2013-macbook-pro/&quot;&gt;building a hassle-free Thunderbolt 2 eGPU&lt;/a&gt; for my late-2013 15” Macbook Pro. In all this time—with the caveat that I was exclusively using an external monitor through Bootcamp—I’ve had essentially zero issues with the setup. Booting would occasionally require one or two attempts to hear the Mac chime, but once you were in, performance was flawless. The GTX 1050 Ti was quite an excellent little card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, my power requirements recently changed. When the Oculus Rift went on sale for $350, I just couldn’t resist picking one up. VR was new to me and I wasn’t sure if this was something that would stick, but my first experience with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MPxd1tD8tuc&quot;&gt;Beat Saber&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7EtQh2keQbY&quot;&gt;The Climb&lt;/a&gt; left me in awe. This was, very clearly, &lt;em&gt;a new category of human experience&lt;/em&gt; that was being offered for just a few hundred bucks! Unfortunately, latecy was now an issue with some of the higher-caliber games such as Batman: Arkham VR, and 60–90fps was essentially a hard requirement for VR immersion. Together with the fact that many newer titles were starting to see poor performance even at lower settings and resolutions, I decided to explore upgrade options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, I had my eye on the single-fan EVGA &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2mOFMv9&quot;&gt;GTX 1060 SC&lt;/a&gt; to eventually replace my 1050 Ti, since the dimensions were very similar. But in doing this round of research, I was surprised to discover that Gigabyte offered an actual, full-fledged &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2NFE0HO&quot;&gt;GTX 1080&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; the same form factor! Though slightly too tall to fit, the card was just the right length for my AKiTiO case, meaning that I could simply take the top off and pop it in without having to do any &lt;a href=&quot;https://imgur.com/a/4nL8e&quot;&gt;metal-bending&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2018/07/25/egpu-redux/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2018 03:32:38 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2018/07/25/egpu-redux/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2018/07/25/egpu-redux/</guid>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Native Art Gallery for Your Mac (Take 2)</title>
        <description>
&lt;div class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://archagon.net/images/blog/bgbuddy/header.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge: fit a rotating art gallery somewhere into my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love visual art and find it hugely inspiring. Unfortunately, reading art books is too much of a context switch to be a regular distraction, while museums are only appropriate for the rare trip. Instagram helps, but it only lets you see content from artists you follow. There’s still the 99% of art history beyond that sliver!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sourcing art wasn’t the problem. For years, I had been keeping a fairly large folder of inspiring images from places such as Imgur albums, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rutracker.org/forum/viewforum.php?f=1643&quot;&gt;RuTracker museum collections&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/ImaginaryNetwork/&quot;&gt;/r/ImaginaryNetwork&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/museum/&quot;&gt;/r/museum&lt;/a&gt;. But leafing through them wasn’t enough: I needed to put them into a regular and random rotation in a place that was just out of eyeshot, but without becoming an overt distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I finally solved the problem by building an app called &lt;a href=&quot;http://backgroundifier.archagon.net&quot;&gt;Backgroundifier&lt;/a&gt;, which converted arbitrary-size images into wallpapers by superimposing them onto attractive, blurred backgrounds. By pairing an &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/09/19/turning-your-macos-desktop-into-a-rotating-art-gallery-with-backgroundifier/&quot;&gt;Automator Folder Action with the native wallpaper cycling functionality of macOS&lt;/a&gt;, I could now drop arbitrary images into a directory on my desktop and have them automatically show up in my wallpaper rotation. Peeking at an image was as simple as invoking the Show Desktop shortcut, and if I wanted to see something new, all I had to do was switch to a new Space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For several years, this scheme worked perfectly fine. But recently, my collection had grown to over 500 images, and I found myself bumping into some slight annoyances. For example, I had no way to retrieve the filename of the current wallpaper, to remove an image from rotation, or to mark it as a favorite. Every maintenance task had to be performed manually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I decided to build a menu bar app that would solve all my problems through a unified interface: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/archagon/backgroundifier-buddy/releases&quot;&gt;BackgroundifierBuddy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2018/05/02/a-native-art-gallery-for-your-mac/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2018/05/02/a-native-art-gallery-for-your-mac/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2018/05/02/a-native-art-gallery-for-your-mac/</guid>
        
        
        <category>releases</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data Laced with History: Causal Trees &amp; Operational CRDTs</title>
        <description>
&lt;div class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://archagon.net/images/blog/causal-trees/header.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;(Sorry about the length! At some point in the distant past, this was supposed to be a short blog post. If you like, you can skip straight to the &lt;a href=&quot;#demo-concurrent-editing-in-macos-and-ios&quot;&gt;demo section&lt;/a&gt; to get a sense of what this article is about.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embarrassingly, most of my app development to date has been confined to local devices. Programmers like to gloat about the stupendous mental castles they build of their circuitous, multi-level architectures, but not me. In truth, networks leave me quite perplexed. I start thinking about data serializing to bits, servers performing their arcane handshakes and voting rituals, merge conflicts pushing into app-space and starting the whole process over again—and it all just turns to mush in my head. For peace of mind, my code needs to be &lt;em&gt;locally provable&lt;/em&gt;, and this means things like idempotent functions, decoupled modules, contiguous data structures, immutable objects. Networks, unfortunately, throw a giant wrench in the works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime last year, after realizing that most of my document-based apps would probably need to support sync and collaboration in the future, I decided to finally take a stab at the problem. Granted, there were tons of frameworks that promised to do the hard work of data model replication for me, but I didn’t want to black-box the most important part of my code. My gut told me that there had to be some arcane bit of foundational knowledge that would allow me to sync my documents in a refined and functional way, decoupled from the stateful spaghetti of the underlying network layer. Instead of downloading a Github framework and &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2iigBOI&quot;&gt;smacking the build button&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to develop a base set of skills that would allow me to easily network &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; document-based app in the future, even if I was starting from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2018/03/24/data-laced-with-history/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2018/03/24/data-laced-with-history/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2018/03/24/data-laced-with-history/</guid>
        
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bluetooth Headphone Sound-Off: Audio-Technica, Sony, Bowers &amp; Wilkins, V-MODA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/bluetooth-headphones/table.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am once again in the market for Bluetooth headphones. My last pair, the first edition Sony MDR-1RBT, served me very well for the last four-and-a-half years. I didn’t (and still don’t) have much experience with the high end of the audio market, but when I was picking them out, they were among the best sounding headphones I’d heard. The feeling of space was especially startling: for the first time in a headphone, I felt like the music was all around me instead of being localized to a point between my ears. Now, parts of it were held together with glue and the remaining pleather was flaking all over my jacket. The time was right for an upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to research comparable, $200 to $400 over-ear wireless replacements. My wishlist included noise cancellation, multi-device pairing, volume controls that interfaced with your device, tactile controls with previous/next buttons, and foldability. The only real technical requirements were audio quality, a zero-latency wired connection, and at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kind of physical control. But non-technical, quality-of-life attributes were also very important. It’s hard to deny that headphones play many important roles in our lives apart from simply reproducing audio. They are most certainly a fashion item. They serve as earmuffs in cold weather. They block out the outside world when we need to retreat into our work. For many of us, they’ve become one of the most important and frequently used accessories in our wardrobe! Soon, we’ll be seeing health and fitness sensors incorporated right into the earcups. Especially with the cord cut, there’s a lot more to headphones than just audio these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2017/12/08/bluetooth-headphone-sound-off/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2017 01:38:07 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2017/12/08/bluetooth-headphone-sound-off/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2017/12/08/bluetooth-headphone-sound-off/</guid>
        
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MX Master Continued: Mouse Latency Measurements</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the course of doing latency testing for &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/05/22/almost-winning-the-wireless-mouse-game-logitech-mx-master/&quot;&gt;my previous article&lt;/a&gt; on the Logitech MX Master, I discovered a couple of flaws in my helper app, and I also realized that I should have probably recorded a few more sample points. So now, as a followup, I have devised a better testing methodology and run a full suite of tests. Unfortunately, with this new data in hand, I must now retract my original recommendation. The Master is still a good mouse for the average user, but its wireless performance is just too unreliable for precise gaming or Bluetooth use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a great all-arounder, I would instead give my highest recommendation to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2uDAeF2&quot;&gt;G403 Wireless&lt;/a&gt;, which I’ve been happily using for several months with zero issues. While this mouse does require a dongle and only has a tenth of the Master’s battery life, its best-in-class performance, non-existent latency, svelte form factor, and incredible clicky side buttons more than make up for these downsides. Better yet, you can routinely find it on sale for $50 or lower on Amazon and at Best Buy. I’ll try to post a fuller account sometime in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, here are the new test results for the MX Master, G602, and MX 518.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2017/05/24/mx-master-continued-mouse-latency-measurements/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 21:55:52 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2017/05/24/mx-master-continued-mouse-latency-measurements/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2017/05/24/mx-master-continued-mouse-latency-measurements/</guid>
        
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>(Almost) Winning the Wireless Mouse Game: Logitech MX Master</title>
        <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mx-master/master-top.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We all know that Bluetooth has an abundance of flaws, ranging from frustrating latency to arcane pairing rituals. By many measures, it still feels like a technology stuck in the early 90’s. And yet, once you’ve experienced the freedom of going wireless, it’s very hard to go back to the old ways. Reaching to unplug your headphones when leaving your desk, only to realize that you can simply walk away? Bliss!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For several years, I’ve been on the lookout for a Bluetooth mouse that could also be used for non-casual gaming. At minimum, the mouse needed to be on par with my trusty &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2qbhqeY&quot;&gt;MX 518&lt;/a&gt; at 1600 DPI and have little to no latency. Unfortunately, the vast majority of reputable Bluetooth mice maxed out at around 1000 DPI and had a reputation for being a bit laggy. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2qbb8fi&quot;&gt;Razer Orochi&lt;/a&gt; was one of the few models that supported high DPI over Bluetooth, but it was a cramped little thing that felt rather unpleasant to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2017/05/22/almost-winning-the-wireless-mouse-game-logitech-mx-master/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2017 13:14:48 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2017/05/22/almost-winning-the-wireless-mouse-game-logitech-mx-master/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2017/05/22/almost-winning-the-wireless-mouse-game-logitech-mx-master/</guid>
        
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Even Better Travel Gaiwan</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/klean-kanteen-gaiwan/front.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, I wrote about the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/12/26/the-perfect-travel-gaiwan/&quot;&gt;Asobu Travel Mug&lt;/a&gt; as an excellent (if unintentional) travel gaiwan. Now, there’s a new leader in the not-a-gaiwan-but-almost-better-than-one category: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2j2ie1U&quot;&gt;Klean Kanteen 8oz insulated tumbler&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2017/01/08/an-even-better-travel-gaiwan/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 13:41:34 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2017/01/08/an-even-better-travel-gaiwan/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2017/01/08/an-even-better-travel-gaiwan/</guid>
        
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MusicMessages! Making a Collaborative Sequencer for iMessage</title>
        <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/music-messages/banner.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, I released an unusual little app for iMessage. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://musicmessages.io&quot;&gt;MusicMessages!&lt;/a&gt;, and it’s a collaborative step sequencer that lets you work on short pieces of music together with your friends. As far as I can tell, it’s the only app of its kind in the iMessage App Store. (Probably for good reason!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2017/01/03/musicmessages-making-a-collaborative-sequencer-for-imessage/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 15:09:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2017/01/03/musicmessages-making-a-collaborative-sequencer-for-imessage/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2017/01/03/musicmessages-making-a-collaborative-sequencer-for-imessage/</guid>
        
        
        <category>releases</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cheap and Painless eGPU Thrills on a 2013 MacBook Pro</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/egpu/egpu.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My late-2013 15” MacBook Pro’s discrete GPU — an NVIDIA GeForce GT 750M — was pretty good for gaming during the first year of its life.  But around the time that the new generation of consoles dropped, AAA games on the PC started becoming unplayable, even at postage-stamp resolutions with the lowest possible settings. I lived on a strict diet of indie games from 2015 to 2016 — thank goodness for well-tuned titles like Overwatch and The Witness! — but the itch to try games like the new Mirror’s Edge and Deus Ex became too great. Initially, I thought it might be time to switch out my MacBook for the upcoming 2016 model, but the winter reveal wasn’t particularly tempting: CPU performance was about the same as mine and the GPU was — at best — 3 times as powerful. (Still need to see the benchmarks on that — educated guess.) Worth it for a few hundred bucks, but $2000? No way!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a gaming PC wasn’t an option due to my mobile lifestyle, and in any case the kind of CPU I could buy for cheap would be comically underpowered compared to the i7 4850HQ I already had in front of me. So I started looking into the scary world of external Thunderbolt GPUs, colloquially known as eGPU. Modern Thunderbolt 3 (allegedly) supports external GPUs in an official capacity, but older Thunderbolt 2 can get the job done as well, even though it’s unsanctioned by Intel. I’m usually reluctant to pursue these sorts of under-the-radar hobbyist projects, but there was enough prior art to make it worth a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2016/12/31/cheap-and-painless-egpu-thrills-on-a-2013-macbook-pro/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 18:18:54 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2016/12/31/cheap-and-painless-egpu-thrills-on-a-2013-macbook-pro/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2016/12/31/cheap-and-painless-egpu-thrills-on-a-2013-macbook-pro/</guid>
        
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Turning Your macOS Desktop into a Rotating Art Gallery with Backgroundifier</title>
        <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/backgroundifier-gallery/title_2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The category of static visual art is in a bit of an awkward phase right now. Entertainment in the 21st century has evolved to actively engage our minds and senses, to the point where movies, music, games, and even audiobooks require little more than putting on a pair of headphones or fixing our vision to the nearest screen. Where does the immense body of work from genres such as fine art, photography, and illustration fit into this world? Museums — physical beasts that they are — can hardly be visited on a whim, and as of yet there’s (sadly) no Spotify for visual art. Meanwhile, hundreds of amazing works are posted daily on Instagram, DeviantArt, and Reddit. How do we find the time to fit them into our content-saturated lives? And how do we return to view the works we’ve already enjoyed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://archagon.net/blog/2016/09/19/turning-your-macos-desktop-into-a-rotating-art-gallery-with-backgroundifier/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more-inside&quot;&gt;Continue Reading...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 16:10:16 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://archagon.net/blog/2016/09/19/turning-your-macos-desktop-into-a-rotating-art-gallery-with-backgroundifier/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://archagon.net/blog/2016/09/19/turning-your-macos-desktop-into-a-rotating-art-gallery-with-backgroundifier/</guid>
        
        
        <category>releases</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
